

Mehmet Mert Yıldıran

Istanbul / Turkey

E-mail: me@mertyildiran.com
Website: mertyildiran.com

SUMMARY

You can checkout **my personal website** to see everything in detail: https://mertyildiran.com

LinkedIn:

https://www.linkedin.com/in/mertyildiran

My StackOverflow profile page:

https://stackoverflow.com/users/2104879/mertyildiran

Also you can checkout my accounts and activities on **Stack Exchange** Communities with these links:

https://stackexchange.com/users/2409365/mertyildiran?tab=accounts https://stackexchange.com/users/2409365/mertyildiran?tab=activity

GitHub:

https://github.com/mertyildiran

I'm the creator of Chaos Programming Language:

https://chaos-lang.org/

I'm a minor contributor to **Wikipedia**'s source code and I have added live streaming feature to **3Blue1Brown**'s math animation library:

https://github.com/wikimedia/mediawiki/commit/4951c2b54f429037038cca617eb3e5860c1c271https://github.com/3b1b/manim/commits?author=mertyildiran

Also I'm a seller on CodeCanyon Marketplace:

https://codecanyon.net/user/mertyildiran/portfolio

Lastly, I'm one of the Turkish Translation Maintainers of Moodle:

https://lang.moodle.org/local/amos/credits.php#credits-language-tr

MY WORK STYLE

I currently use VS Code with 197 extensions installed. I also have an IDE-like Neovim setup that I occasionally use. You can find all of my personal configurations in my dotfiles repository. I'm kind of anti-JetBrains for the sake of open-source so I don't use PhpStorm, PyCharm, CLion etc. Please let me share a screenshot of my current VS Code setup: https://github.com/mertyildiran/dotfiles

https://i.ibb.co/StKwkcr/Screenshot-20200111-010320.png

I rather choose command-line tools over GUI in almost every occasion. For example, I connect to freenode.net using WeeChat IRC client. I almost always interact with databases via terminal. I love the convenience of having ohmyzsh, Powerlevel9k, fzf etc. under my finger tips:

https://weechat.org/

https://github.com/ohmyzsh/ohmyzsh

https://github.com/Powerlevel9k/powerlevel9k

https://github.com/junegunn/fzf

Mehmet Mert Vilduran

I have great experience in managing issue trackers, Kanban boards etc. of GitHub, GitLab, Trello, Jira, Phabricator and so on. Also I'm experienced in managing technical personnel.

I always work from desktop computers. I've been using KDE neon since its initial release June 2016, before that I hopped from a lot of different Ubuntu flavors to flavors and decided to land on KDE neon.

I use a specific keyboard and mouse pair to maintain my muscle memory. I've been using SteelSeries Apex M400 and Microsoft Classic Intellimouse in both my workplace and home for many years. These two product lines are quite stable so I always find the same keyboard and mouse in the market:

https://steelseries.com/gaming-keyboards/apex-m400

https://www.microsoft.com/accessories/en-us/products/mice/microsoft-classic-intellimouse

I always have necessary linting tools / code sniffers, language servers up with my VS Code or Neovim setup. So I expect CI to have these checks too, if they are missing then I add them. It's kind of a must for me.

I would like to document the code with comments and docblocks in general but sometimes it's becoming impossible because of deadlines.

Also I like to write unit tests, feature tests, end-to-end API tests, fuzzing tests, Valgrind and Clang sanitizer checks since I believe in the necessity of test driven development.

WORK EXPERIENCE

UP9, Inc.

Aug 2020 — Present

Software Engineer

https://up9.com/ Palo Alto, California, United States (part-time)

Wrote compilers that targeting JavaScript, Java and Python.

Vademecum A.Ş.

Jul 2020 — Sep 2020

Senior PHP Developer

https://www.vademecumonline.com.tr Istanbul, Turkey

Worked as short-term contractor, on a project that has a tech stack: Yii 2 PHP Framework and PostgreSQL database. Solved critical performance problems in a distributed PostgreSQL cluster using materialized views and various query optimization techniques.

Macellan

Jul 2019 — Jun 2020

PHP Techinal Lead

https://macellan.net/ Istanbul, Turkey

Developed and maintained things like critical payment and business logic, monitoring tools on Havaist mobile application's backend. Coordinated a developer team of four. Implemented alerts, periodic backups. Improved the development team's workflow with proper issue tracking and extensive testing.

The backend were consists of multiple Laravel application designed with the microservice architecture.

Since it holds a critical payment system and a POS API, achieved proper deployment cycles and continuous integration. We have leveraged the project and the team to a stable and successful phase.

My team is also maintained the backend of Tedas Aydinlatma mobile application which is written in Symfony 4, for a short period of time.

Macellan

Mar 2019 — Jun 2019

Senior PHP Developer https://macellan.net/ Istanbul, Turkey

Developed face and speech recognition features for a digital archiving service called Macellan Digital Archieve which is written on top of Laravel framework. Upgraded that project from 4.2 to 5.8 which was an challenging work. Created LaraUp in the meantime. Then forked that project, implemented multitenancy and turned into SaaS. Deployed that fork as Turkcell Digital Archieve in the name of Turkcell. Integrated that SaaS to Turkcell's CRM(called SOL Maya) via a SOAP API described by Turkcell.

Built and trained a TensorFlow model to recognize hand-written signatures and validate them using biometric data from signed PDFs on Samsung Galaxy tablets and S Pen. The PDFs were encrypted using some native Java libraries so I have created a Java program to decrypt the PDFs. Product's itself was actually a Windows Form Application so I have to pack three different programs written in three languages(C#, Java, Python) to an installer. This was also a challenging project.

Motiwe

Dec 2018 — Feb 2019

System Software Engineer https://www.motiwe.com/ Istanbul, Turkey

Developed a state-of-the-art, very YouTube-like video sharing and live streaming platform in Node.js on top of Express framework. Wrote high performance, fail-safe video transcoding cron jobs. Used front-end technologies like AngularJS, Angular, jQuery, Spectre.css, Bootstrap, SCSS and so on. Worked with Nginx on caching and load balancing. Did a lot of On-Premise installations to a wide variety of enterprise companies in Istanbul, Turkey.

Dragon Computer

Aug 2015 — Nov 2018

Artificial Intelligence Specialist https://dragon.computer/ Istanbul, Turkey

Created a virtual assistant called Dragonfire which is one of the most well known open-source virtual assistants in the world.

Used tons of different technologies and libraries that formed mainly around C and Python programming languages.

Did the containerization of Dragonfire using Docker.

Programmed an Android client for the virtual assistant in Java language.

telve.net

Aug 2016 — Sep 2018

Full Stack Developer https://telve.net/ Istanbul, Turkey

Developed one of the best if not the best Reddit clone using Codelgniter framework. This project is also open-source.

Turkish Land Forces

Nov 2017 — Apr 2018

Infantry Sergeant
Mandatory Military Service
Balıkesir, Turkey

Served as the adjutant of a Captain under infantry class. Learned how to use, aim and care Heckler & Koch G3 select-fire battle rifle. Did a lot of sports and night watch/duty shifts.

Samulaş A.Ş.

Jun 2015 — Aug 2015

Software Engineer Intern (Urban Transportation) IT Department http://samulas.com.tr/ Samsun, Turkey

Ondokuz Mayıs University

Jun 2014 — Aug 2014

System Administrator Intern IT Department http://bidb.omu.edu.tr/en Samsun, Turkey

EDUCATION

Electrical and Electronics Engineering

Sep 2020 — Present

Kadir Has University Master's degree

https://sgs.khas.edu.tr/en/programs/master-degree-programmes/msc-in-electronics-engineering/about-the-program

Physics

May 2018 — Jun 2020

Boğaziçi University Bachelor's degree

https://phys.boun.edu.tr

Computer Engineering

Sep 2012 — Aug 2016

Ondokuz Mayıs University Bachelor's degree

http://bil.muhendislik.omu.edu.tr/en

Natural and Applied Sciences

Sep 2005 — Jun 2009

Samsun Ataturk Anatolian High School High school degree

http://samsunaal.meb.k12.tr/

INTERESTS

Computer Science Related: Web Programming, Operating Systems, Lexers, Parsers, Compilers, FPGAs, Machine Learning, Computational Science, Computational Linguistics, Audio Signal Processing, Quantum Computing

Others: Dark Matter and Dark Energy Physics, General Relativity, Standard Model, String

Mehmet Mert Vildiran

REFERENCES

References available upon request.

FOREIGN LANGUAGES

Early life: TÖMER English Courses degree

http://tomer.ankara.edu.tr/

Proficient in English with a **BUEPT degree**.

Score: B

http://www.yadyok.boun.edu.tr/buept/

Also interested in learning Japanese, German and Russian.

PROJECTS

The Chaos Programming Language

a purely functional programming language that achieves zero cyclomatic complexity https://github.com/chaos-lang/chaos

Plexus

a novel object-oriented approach to the artificial neural networks inspired by synaptic plasticity between biological neurons

https://github.com/mertyildiran/Plexus

Dragonfire:

Dragonfire is an open source virtual assistant project for Ubuntu based Linux distributions https://github.com/mertyildiran/Dragonfire

Dermatron:

Dermatology focused medical records software, augmented with computer vision and artificial intelligence [Meteor packaged with Electron]

https://github.com/mertyildiran/Dermatron

DASM:

Dragon Assembler, a simple assembler for a made-up microprocessor architecture https://github.com/mertyildiran/DASM

Unleash:

A linux shell written in C

https://github.com/mertyildiran/Unleash

CERTIFICATES

freeCodeCamp Front End Developer Certificate

Quincy Larson

https://www.freecodecamp.org/certification/mertyildiran/legacy-front-end

Windows Phone Certificate of Achievement

Turkcell Developers of The Future

https://gelecegiyazanlar.turkcell.com.tr/kisi/mehmetmertyildiran/belge/windows-phone-201

Android Certificate of Achievement

Turkcell Developers of The Future

https://gelecegiyazanlar.turkcell.com.tr/kisi/mehmetmertyildiran/belge/android-401

iOS Certificate of Achievement

Turkcell Developers of The Future

https://gelecegiyazanlar.turkcell.com.tr/kisi/mehmetmertyildiran/belge/ios-101

Startup Weekend Samsun

United Nations Development Programme Workshop Certificate of Attendance http://mertyildiran.com/images/certificates/07.jpg

Cinema Certificate

Bosphorus University Mithat Alam Film Center, 2011 Movie Workshop Certificate of Attendance http://mertyildiran.com/images/certificates/08.jpg

ADDTIONAL INFO

Driving License: B

Military Service : Completed

Smoking: Yes

Health Problem: None

Children: None

Marital Status: Married